<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
  Copyright (C) Nginx, Inc.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../dtd/article.dtd">

<article name="Setting up nginx environment on Amazon EC2"
         link="/en/docs/howto_setup_development_environment_on_ec2.html"
         lang="en"
         rev="2">

<section name="Products available on Amazon EC2">

<para>
As a Standard Technology Partner participating in AWS Partner Network,
Nginx is offering the following products:

<list type="bullet" compact="no">

<listitem>
<link url="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00A04GAG4">
NGINX AMI based on Amazon Linux AMI</link>
</listitem>

<listitem>
Latest version of nginx optimized for use with AWS
</listitem>

<listitem>
Install script for typical nginx configurations with AWS
</listitem>

</list>

</para>

</section>

<section id="setting_up_nginx_environment_on_aws"
         name="Step-by-step guide to start working with NGINX AMI">

<para>
To quickly set up nginx environment on AWS:
<list type="bullet" compact="no">
<listitem>
Follow
<link url="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/latest/GettingStartedGuide/Welcome.html">
Getting Started with EC2</link> guide to sign up to AWS and
get more information about EC2 itself.
Then you can proceed to
<link url="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00A04GAG4">
NGINX AMI product page on AWS Marketplace</link> and launch NGINX AMI.
When configuring the firewall rules, it is necessary to add a rule
to accept web traffic on TCP ports 80 and 443 (“1-click launch”
will do that automatically).
</listitem>

<listitem>
As soon as the new instance is launched, nginx will be automatically
started and configured to serve default index.html page.
You can check it by pointing your web browser to the public DNS
name of your newborn EC2 instance.
Also, you can log in to your instance and use
<programlisting>
/etc/init.d/nginx status
</programlisting>
to check the status of your nginx server.
</listitem>

<listitem>
To configure nginx for use with different web frameworks
quickly and efficiently, you can use a special helper script
included in NGINX AMI.
Log in to your EC2 instance and start:

<programlisting>
nginx-setup
</programlisting>
</listitem>

<listitem>
You will be asked to select what components to install.
Please check the next section in this document for
list of available software components.
After you have selected the necessary component, the script
will automatically install all prerequisite packages
and prepare the necessary configuration.
There will be a separate user created too,
and then a sample web application is started to ensure everything
is working correctly.
</listitem>

<listitem>
After the installation completes and the web application is installed
in a subdirectory inside <path>/var/www</path>,
additional instructions will be provided on how to start/stop sample
application.
For example, the Rails/Unicorn application will reside in
<path>/var/www/rails/sample-unicorn</path>, and specific part of nginx
configuration will be in <path>/etc/nginx/conf.d/rails-unicorn.conf</path>.
Installed application and configuration files can be used as a basis
for further development.
</listitem>
</list>
</para>

</section>

<section id="available_software"
         name="Software available for automatic configuration with NGINX AMI">

<para>
The following software is available for automatic installation
and configuration using <literal>nginx-setup</literal> helper script:

<list type="bullet" compact="no">

<listitem>
Generic
<link url="http://php.net/manual/en/install.fpm.php">PHP-FPM</link>
configuration.
FPM (FastCGI Process Manager) is an alternative PHP FastCGI implementation
with some additional features useful for heavy-loaded sites, such as
dynamic/static child spawning, advanced process management,
ability to start workers with different uid/gid/chroot environment.
</listitem>

<listitem>
<link url="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</link>,
an open-source Ruby web framework that's optimized for programmer happiness
and sustainable productivity.
You can choose the application server to work with, currently
Unicorn and Thin are available to configure.
Also, during the installation process you can either enter the version of
Rails manually, or use the default one.
</listitem>

<listitem>
<link url="https://www.djangoproject.com/">Django</link>,
a high-level Python web framework that encourages rapid development
and clean, pragmatic design.
It lets you build high-performing, elegant Web applications quickly.
Django focuses on automating as much as possible and adhering to the DRY
(Don't Repeat Yourself) principle.
</listitem>

<listitem>
<link url="http://www.pylonsproject.org/">Pyramid</link>,
a small, fast, down-to-earth, open source Python web development framework.
It makes real-world web application development and deployment more fun,
more predictable, and more productive.
Pyramid is a Pylons Project, and is the successor to the Pylons web framework.
There is an ability to enter desired version of Pyramid during the
installation process.
</listitem>

</list>

</para>

</section>

<section id="if_something_goes_wrong"
         name="What if something goes wrong?">

<para>
In case you encounter any problems with nginx configuration,
the documentation is available on
<link url="http://nginx.org/en/docs/">http://nginx.org/en/docs/</link>.
</para>

<para>
Customers purchased NGINX AMI at AWS Marketplace are eligible for assistance
under AWS support plan by Nginx described here:
<link url="http://nginx.com/support.html">http://nginx.com/support.html</link>.
Please note that you will need your AWS Account Number in order to activate
your support plan.
In some cases we may also ask you to provide EC2 instance ID(s).
</para>

</section>

</article>
